Shiva FARASHAHI, Ph.D.

Machine Learning | Data Science shiva.farashahi@gmail.com

I am a machine learning expert, with 9+ years of applying machine learning tools. Proficient in statistical analysis of large datasets, machine learning approaches, and scripting languages including Python.

EMPLOYMENT

1/2024-present Associate Principle, Machine Learning

6/2022-1/2024 Senior Machine Learning Engineer

Harbinger Health, Flagship Pioneering, MA, USA

10/2019-6/2022 Flatiron Research Fellow

Center for Computational Neuroscience, Flatiron Institute, NY, USA

PROFESSIONAL SKILLS

Programming Python, Pandas, Scikit-Learn, SciPy, NumPy, TensorFlow, PyTorch, MLFlow, SQL

Machine Learning Regression, Classification, Clustering, Latent variable/Dimensionality reduction

models, Ensemble methods, Reinforcement Learning, Convolutional Neural

Networks, Transformer models, Time-series analysis

Additional Amazon AWS, Study design and measurement (Power analysis, A/B testing,

Experimental design), Biophysical modeling of brain dynamics

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Harbinger Health, Associate Principle, Machine Learning

- Developed Transformer models tailored for methylation-based cancer detection at the read level.
- Collaborated in design and implementation of Transfer learning models for pan-cancer classification.
- Developed a robust data augmentation method to enhance generalization of ML models.
- Established end-to-end ML pipeline to enable tracking, training, and deploying of models at scale.
- *Tools:* Python, PyTorch, TensorFlow, Transformers, Convolutional Neural Networks, Transfer Learning, Hierarchical Classification, MLFlow, AWS SageMaker.

Flatiron Institute, Flatiron Research Fellow

- Analyzed large neural recordings and behavioral data to investigate continual learning in rodents.
- Investigated stability of learned representations in a biologically plausible Neural Network during noisy continual learning.
- Tools: Python, SciPy, NumPy, Time-series analysis.

Dartmouth College, Ph.D. Computational Neuroscience

- Developed a meta-learning Reinforcement Learning agent and explored its behavior in various tasks.
- Designed a Recurrent Neural Network based Reinforcement Learning agent to explore adaptation of generalizable representations.
- Tools: Python, TensorFlow, Reinforcement Learning, Latent variable models, Study design.

EDUCATION

9/2014-8/2019 Ph.D. in Computational Neuroscience

Department of Psychological and Brain Sciences, Dartmouth College, NH, USA

9/2011-6/2013 M.S. in Biomedical Engineering

School of ECE, University of Tehran, Tehran, Iran

9/2007-9/2011 B.S. in Control systems Engineering

Department of EE, Ferdowsi University of Mashhad, Khorasan, Iran

SELECTED PUBLICATIONS

- 8. Qin S, **Farashahi S**, Lipshutz D, Sengupta A, Chklovskii D, Pehlevan C (2023). Coordinated drift of receptive fields in Hebbian/anti-Hebbian network models during noisy representation learning. *Nature Neuroscience*, 1-11.
- 7. **Farashahi S**, Soltani A (2021). Computational mechanisms of distributed value representations and mixed learning strategies, *Nature Communications*, 12, 7191.
- 6. Friedrich J, Golkar S, **Farashahi S**, Genkin A, Sengupta A, Chklovskii D (2021). Neural optimal feedback control with local learning rules. *Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems*, 34.
- 5. **Farashahi S**, Donahue C, Hayden B, Lee D, Soltani A (2019) Flexible combination of reward information across primates. *Nature human behaviour*, 3(11), 1215-1224.
- 4. **Farashahi S**, Azab H, Hayden B, Soltani A (2018). On the flexibility of basic risk attitudes in monkeys. *Journal of Neuroscience*, 38(18), 4383-4398.
- 3. **Farashahi S**, Rowe K, Aslami Z, Lee D, Soltani A (2017). Feature-based learning improves adaptability without compromising precision. *Nature Communications*, 8(1), 1-16.
- 2. **Farashahi S**, Seo H, Donahue C, Khorsand P, Lee D, Soltani A (2017). Metaplasticity as a neural substrate for adaptive learning and choice under uncertainty. *Neuron*, 94(2), 401-414.
- 1. Soltani A, Khorsand P, Guo C, **Farashahi S**, Liu J (2016). Neural Substrates of Cognitive Biases during Probabilistic Inference. *Nature Communications*, 7(1), 1-14.